Finding Aid for the Peter Plagens papers LSC.2255
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Notebooks and Datebooks, 1995-2013
  - Mailing list and address book floppies, 2006, 2008 (Box 31, Folder 16)
    Electronic copies of Plagens' mailing list and address book.
- DRIPS, 1984-2006
  This series contains copies of Plagens' journal entries. These are also referred to as DRPS or DRP, abbreviations for the painter's DRIPS.
  These materials are restricted until three years after the death of Peter Plagens.
  - White Paintings, 1985-1990 (Box 32, Folder 1)
    This folder title refers to a notice in The New Yorker that said, "White paintings, with drips, by the art critic." According to Plagens, "Somehow my drips into a journal seemed to echo the drips (traces of my passing through) on a canvas."
  - DRP, 1991-1998 (Box 33, Folder 1-6, Box 32, Folder 2-6)
    Box 32: 1991-1995
    Box 33: 1996-1998
  - DRPS, 1999-2008 (Box 35, Folder 1-8, Box 34, Folder 1-7)
    Box 34: 1999-2003
    Box 35: 2004-2008
  - DRPS floppies, 1984-2006 (Box 35, Folder 9-10)
    These items are restricted until three years after the death of Peter Plagens.
- Memorabilia, 1938-2013
  This series consists of art work created by Peter's father, George Plagens, publications, flyers, memorial programs, an illustrated trip diary by Walter Gabrielson and Nancy Goldberg, a Newsweek special issue cover which features Peter, a John Marshall High School 40th reunion program and badge, a file of humorous annotated clippings for painter Doug Hilson, a North Carolina personalized license plate, materials from Plagens' studio walls, his Columbia University National Arts Journalism certificate and September 11, 2001 notes written on an empty cigarettes pack.
  - George Plagens' art work, 1938, undated (Box 36, Folder 1)
    These three pieces, created by Plagens' father who worked as a freelance commercial artist, are futuristic imaginings of airplanes, a pilot and an automobile. According to Peter, the sum of George H. Plagens' formal training was a few night classes at the Cleveland Art Institute.
  - George Plagens' cartoon, 1938 (Box 37, Folder 1)
    Framed cartoon by Plagens' father, published in Collier's magazine, depicting window washers harnessed to a building while shooting at birds with water guns. The caption reads, "Tsk Tsk! Missed again!"
  - Lucky Strike cigarettes pack, circa 1940s (Box 37, Folder 2)
    Cigarettes pack created by George H. Plagens, who created samples such as this to add to his portfolio while he searched for freelance work as a commercial artist.
  - The 1941 Cars clipping (Box 37, Folder 3)
    Painter and friend Doug Hilson gave this clipping to Plagens for his birthday. Hilson is also a Professor of Fine Art at Hofstra University. According to Plagens, Hilson holds a vast collection of vintage postcards and magazines. Examples of these postcards and vintage magazine clippings may be found in the "A Drama In Your Mailbox Production" postcards folder within the Correspondence series of this collection.
  - Clippings and publications, 1973-2005 (Box 37, Folder 4)
    Publications include Two Qualms & a Quirk: Three Stories by Richard de Mille signed by the author, Walter Gabrielson's "The Openings Gambit or For One Night in L.A." text and drawings, The Daily Pigeon newspaper and "The Continuous Mark: 40 Years of the New York Studio School."
    Clippings include "Decline and Resistance: The New Radicalness of the Subject" by Peter Oswald, "Diana, Surrogate Princess" by Barbara Ehrenreich, and "Death Explains Himself" by Roger Rosenblatt. This folder also includes an article on the life and death of basketball player Curtis Conrad and a "Murder on the Midway: Sordid Life and Death of Lobster Boy" article.
  - Untitled publication, 1974 (Box 37, Folder 5)
    Los Angeles art publication with an interview with Plagens at his Pasadena studio.
  - ABSTRART license plate, 1981 (Box 37, Folder 6)
    Biography/History
    Plagens was professor of the fine art and art history department at the University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill from 1980-1984 and chaired this department from 1980-1983. He and wife Laurie Fendrich sublet a place in Chapel Hill their first year and then moved to Durham where they lived in "Peter's Folly," a Jehovah's Witnesses church that Plagens describes as a "...loft on a cement slab." The couple bought a new Honda in 1981 and this was its vanity plate.
  - Hot Flashes quarterly, 1993 (Box 37, Folder 7)
    This premiere issue by the Guerilla Girls, self-described "feminist masked avengers," is devoted to their examination of The New York Times' art critics. The publication's tagline is "All the sexism, racism and homophobia that fits, we complain about."
  - Memorial programs, 1994, 2000, 2004 (Box 37, Folder 8)
    Memorial programs for Newsweek editor, critic and writer Jack Kroll, Robert Paul Tavetian, and artist John Coplans, founder and former editor of Artforum magazine.
  - Diary of a Small Journey, 1995 (Box 37, Folder 9)
    One photocopy of Walter Gabrielson and Nancy Goldberg's illustrated diary of their trip to Paris and Italy, and photocopies of Gabrielson's cartoon work from the 1960s.
  - Hilson file, 1995-2000 (Box 37, Folder 10)
    Plagens' humorous file for his friend, painter Doug Hilson contains Hall 'O' Fame materials that include witty annotations on clippings, invitations and photographs concerning art openings, lectures, Donald Judd's work at the Chinati Foundation, and going to the movies with Pee Wee Herman.
  - Nova International Enterprise flyer, undated (Box 37, Folder 11)
    This flyer lists a Post Office Box in the Bronx to write to for "Financing to Start or Spand Your Business. Free Details." Plagens picked this up off the street because of the strange use of the word "spand."
  - Newsweek cover, 2002 May 31 (Box 36, Folder 9)
    One color photocopy of a Newsweek Special Issue cover with a photographic portrait of Plagens features the following headline and subhead: "Van Goghing, Van Goghn: Peter Gives Us a Brush With Greatness."
  - JMHS Reunion program, 1998 (Box 37, Folder 12)
    Plagens' 40 Year John Marshall High School Reunion program includes his laminated photo badge.
  - Columbia University certificate, 1999 (Box 37, Folder 13)
    This Columbia University Graduate School of Journalism certificate documents Plagens as one of four senior fellows in the National Arts Journalism Program from August, 1998 to May, 1999.
  - 911 notes, 2001 September 11 (Box 37, Folder 14)
    Plagens found these September 11th notes on the street. An attack timeline is written on the inside of this Newport cigarettes pack.
  - Plagens portrait, 2002 (Box 37, Folder 15)
    Portrait on ruled paper with black ballpoint pen and metallic blue pen. Plagens recalls that he is unsure of the artist but it may have been his wife, Laurie, making a fake Picasso portrait of him.
  - Wall material, undated (Box 37, Folder 16)
    Materials include items that were previously posted on Plagens' studio walls such as a Polaroid photo of his daughter, Phoebe, a photograph of best friend Walter Gabrielson, art by Phoebe, an announcement for a National Gallery of Art press breakfast and restoration preview of the three panels of Gerard David's The Saint Anne Altarpiece, and a poster of the Fifteenth General Staff Course Army Air Forces Group.
  - Bad Boy, 2013 (Box 37, Folder 17)
    This hardcover copy of painter Eric Fischl's autobiography includes annotations by Plagens.